Mobility in developing world cities
التنقل في مدن البلدان النامية
is a very peculiar challenge,
يمثل تحدي مميز جداً ،
because different from health
لأنه باختلافه عن الصحة
or education or housing,
أو التعليم أو السكن،
it tends to get worse as societies become richer.
يميل إلى الأسوء مع ازدياد ثروات المجتمعات.
Clearly, a unsustainable model.
بوضوح، نموذج غير مستدام.
Mobility, as most other developing country problems,
التنقل، مثل معظم المشاكل الأخرى في البلدان النامية،
more than a matter of money or technology,
أكثر من كونها مسألة مال أو تكنولوجيا،
is a matter of equality, equity.
هي مسألة مساواة وإنصاف.
The great inequality in developing countries
التفاوت الطبقي الكبير في البلدان النامية
makes it difficult to see, for example,
يجعل من الصعب أن نرى، على سبيل المثال،
that in terms of transport,
أن في مجال النقل،
an advanced city is not one
المدينة المتقدمة ليست
where even the poor use cars,
التي يركب فيها الفقراء سيارات
but rather one where even the rich
بل أين يستعمل الأغنياء
use public transport.
وسائل النقل العمومية.
Or bicycles: For example, in Amsterdam,
أو الدراجات: على سبيل المثال، في أمستردام،
more than 30 percent of the population
أكثر من 30 بالمئة من السكان
uses bicycles,
يستخدمون الدراجات،
despite the fact that the Netherlands has
على الرغم من أن هولندا لديها
a higher income per capita than the United States.
دخل أعلى للفرد الواحد من الولايات المتحدة.
There is a conflict in developing world cities
هناك صراع في مدن البلدان النامية
for money, for government investment.
على المال و على الإستثمار العام.
If more money is invested in highways,
إذا استثمرت المزيد من الأموال في الطرق السريعة،
of course there is less money for housing,
بطبيعة الحال هناك مال أقل للإسكان،
for schools, for hospitals,
للمدارس و للمستشفيات،
and also there is a conflict for space.
وأيضا هناك صراع على الفضاء.
There is a conflict for space between
هناك صراع على الفضاء
those with cars and those without them.
بين الذين يملكون سيارات وفاقديها.
Most of us accept today
معظمنا متقبل اليوم
that private property and a market economy
أن الملكية الخاصة وإقتصاد السوق
is the best way to manage most of society's resources.
هي أفضل وسيلة لتسيير أغلبية مصادر المجتمع.
However, there is a problem with that,
لكن هناك مشكل في هذا،
that market economy needs
هو أن إقتصاد السوق
inequality of income in order to work.
يحتاج للفارق في الدخل ليعمل.
Some people must make more money,
على بعض الناس أن يجنوا مالاً أكثر،
some others less.
واخرون أن يجنوا أقل.
Some companies succeed. Others fail.
على بعض الشركات أن تنجح. وأخرى أن تفشل.
Then what kind of equality
إذاً في أي نوع من المساواة
can we hope for today
نستطيع أن نأمل اليوم
with a market economy?
مع إقتصاد سوق؟
I would propose two kinds
اقترح نوعان
which both have much to do with cities.
كلاهما متعلق كثيرا بالمدن.
The first one is equality of quality of life,
الأول، المساواة في جودة المعيشة،
especially for children,
خاصةً للأطفال،
that all children should have,
كل الأطفال ينبغي لهم،
beyond the obvious health and education,
بغض النظر على الصحة والتعليم البديهيين،
access to green spaces, to sports facilities,
حق الوصول إلى مساحات خضراء، إلى منشأت رياضية،
to swimming pools, to music lessons.
إلى مسابح، إلى دروس موسيقية.
And the second kind of equality
والنوع الثاني من المساواة
is one which we could call "democratic equality."
هو الذي نستطيع تسميته ب&amp;quot;المساوة الديمقراطية&amp;quot;.
The first article in every constitution states
يصرح البند الأول في أي دستور
that all citizens are equal before the law.
أن كل المواطنين سواسية أمام القانون.
That is not just poetry.
هذا ليس مجرد شعر.
It's a very powerful principle.
إنه مبدأ قوي.
For example, if that is true,
فعلى سبيل المثال، إن كان ذلك صحيح،
a bus with 80 passengers
حافلة ب-80 راكب
has a right to 80 times more road space
لها الحق في 80 مرة ضعف مساحة الطريق
than a car with one.
التي تشغلها سيارة بشخص واحد.
We have been so used to inequality, sometimes,
لقد اعتدنا كثيراً على اللامساواة حتى صرنا أحيانا،
that it's before our noses and we do not see it.
لا نراها وهي أمام أعيننا.
Less than 100 years ago,
قبل ما يقل عن 100 سنة،
women could not vote,
لم يكن يحق للنساء التصويت،
and it seemed normal,
وبدا ذلك طبيعياً،
in the same way that it seems normal today
بنفس الطريقة التي يبدوا فيها طبيعياً اليوم
to see a bus in traffic.
أن نرى حافلة وسط الزحام.
In fact, when I became mayor,
في الحقيقة، حين صرت عمدة،
applying that democratic principle
تطبيق ذلك المبدأ الديمقراطي
that public good prevails over private interest,
أن المنفعة العامة تعم على المصلحة الخاصة،
that a bus with 100 people
أن حافلة ب-100 راكب
has a right to 100 times more road space than a car,
لها الحق في 100 مرة ضعف مساحة الطريق لسيارة،
we implemented a mass transit system
دمجنا نظام نقل جماعي
based on buses in exclusive lanes.
مبني على حافلات في خطوط حصرية.
We called it TransMilenio, in order to make buses sexier.
اطلقنا عليه إسم ترنسميلنيو، حتى نجعل الحافلات أكثر جاذبية.
And one thing is that it is also a very beautiful democratic symbol, because as buses zoom by,
وايظاً هو عبارة عن رمز جميل جداً للديمقراطية، لأنه حين تمر الحافلات،
expensive cars stuck in traffic,
تعلق سيارات فخمة في الزحام،
it clearly is almost a picture of democracy at work.
بوضوح تكاد تكون صورة للديمقراطية في العمل.
In fact, it's not just a matter of equity.
في الحقيقة، هي ليست فقط مسألة إنصاف.
It doesn't take Ph.D.'s.
لا تتطلب دكاترة.
A committee of 12-year-old children
فمجموعة أطفال في الثانية عشرة من عمرهم
would find out in 20 minutes
سيكتشفون في 20 دقيقة
that the most efficient way to use scarce road space
أن الوسيلة الأكثر فعالية لإستعمال فضاء السير النادر
is with exclusive lanes for buses.
هي عن طريق خطوط مخصصة للحفلات.
In fact, buses are not sexy,
في الحقيقة، الحافلات ليست جذابة،
but they are the only possible means
لكنها الوسيلة الوحيدة الممكنة
to bring mass transit to all areas
لإدخال النقل الجماعي إلى كل نواحي
of fast growing developing cities.
المدن النامية السريعة التوسع.
They also have great capacity.
هي أيضا ذو سعة كبيرة.
For example, this system in Guangzhou
على سبيل المثال، ذلك النظام في غوانغزهو
is moving more passengers our direction
يرسل أكثر ركاب في اتجاهنا
than all subway lines in China,
من كل الخطوط في الصين،
except for one line in Beijing,
ما عدا خط وحيد في بايجين،
at a fraction of the cost.
في جزء من التكلفة.
We fought not just for space for buses,
لم نكافح فقط من أجل فضاء للحفلات،
but we fought for space for people,
بل أيضا من أجل فضاء للناس،
and that was even more difficult.
وكان ذلك أكثر صعوبة.
Cities are human habitats,
المدن موئل لإنسان،
and we humans are pedestrians.
ونحن كبشر مشاة.
Just as fish need to swim or birds need to fly
كما يحتاج السمك للسباحة أو الطيور للتحليق
or deer need to run, we need to walk.
أو الأيل للركض، نحتاج نحن للمشي.
There is a really enormous conflict,
هناك حقا صراع ضخم،
when we are talking about developing country cities,
عندما نتحدث عن مدن البلدان النامية،
between pedestrians and cars.
بين المارة والسيارات.
Here, what you see is a picture that shows
ماترونه هنا صورة تظهر
insufficient democracy.
ديمقراطية غير كافية.
What this shows is that people who walk
المبين هنا أنا المارة
are third-class citizens
هم مواطنون من الطبقة الثالثة
while those who go in cars
بينما الذين يتنقلون بالسيارات
are first-class citizens.
هم مواطنون من الطبقة الأولى.
In terms of transport infrastructure,
في ما يتعلق بالبنيات التحتية للنقل،
what really makes a difference
الذي يحدث حقاً فرق
between advanced and backward cities
بين المدن المتقدمة والمتخلفة
is not highways or subways
ليست الطرق السريعة أو انفاق المترو
but quality sidewalks.
بل أرصفة ذات جودة.
Here they made a flyover, probably very useless,
هنا يبنون جسر علوي، عديم الفائدة في غالب الأحيان،
and they forgot to make a sidewalk.
وينسون جعل أرصفة.
This is prevailing all over the world.
وهذا منتشر في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Not even schoolchildren are more important than cars.
حتى التلاميذ ليسوا أكثر أهمية من السيارات.
In my city of Bogotá,
في مدينتي بوغوتا،
we fought a very difficult battle
خضنا معركة صعبة
in order to take space from cars,
لسلب فضاء من السيارات،
which had been parking on sidewalks for decades,
التي كانت تركن على الأرصفة لعقود،
in order to make space for people that should reflect
لجعل مساحة للناس التي من شأنها أن تعكس
dignity of human beings,
كرامة الإنسان،
and to make space for protected bikeways.
وجعل فضاء أيضاً لممرات درجات آمنة.
First of all, I had black hair before that.
أولا، كان شعري أسود قبل خوض هذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I was almost impeached in the process.
وكدت افقد وظيفتي وسط العملية.
It is a very difficult battle.
انها معركة جد صعبة.
However, it was possible, finally,
لكن، ممكنة، في النهاية،
after very difficult battles, to make a city
بعد معارك صعبة لجعل مدينة
that would reflect some respect for human dignity,
قد تعكس بعض الاحترام لكرامة البشر،
that would show that those who walk are equally
التي من شأنها إظهار أن المشاة
important to those who have cars.
من نفس مستوى أهمية الذين يملكون سيارات
Indeed, a very important ideological and political issue anywhere
بالطبع، مشكلة ايدولوجية وسياسية مهمة أياً كان
is how to distribute that most valuable resource
هي كيفية توزيع ذلك المصدر القيم
of a city, which is road space.
في المدينة، وهو الطريق.
A city could find oil or diamonds underground
قد تتضمن مدينة نفطاً أو ألماساً في بطانها
and it would not be so valuable as road space.
ولن يكون ذلك أكثر قيمة من فضاء الطريق.
How to distribute it between pedestrians,
كيف يوزع بين مشاة،
bicycles, public transport and cars?
دراجات، نقل حضري وسيارات؟
This is not a technological issue,
هذه ليست مشكلة تكنولوجية،
and we should remember that in no constitution
ويجب أن تذكر حين نجري ذلك التقسيم
parking is a constitutional right
أنه ما من دستور في العالم،
when we make that distribution.
يعتبر ركن السيارات حق دستوري.
We also built, and this was 15 years ago,
لقد بنينا أيضا، وكان هذا قبل 15 عاماً،
before there were bikeways in New York
قبل أن يكون هنالك طرق للدراجات في نيو يورك
or in Paris or in London,
أو في باريس أو في لندن،
it was a very difficult battle as well,
كانت معركة صعبة أيضاً،
more than 350 kilometers of protected bicycle ways.
بنينا أكثر من 350 كيلومتر من طرق الدراجات المحمية.
I don't think protected bicycle ways
لا أعتقد أن طرق الدراجات المحمية
are a cute architectural feature.
ميزة معمارية جميلة.
They are a right, just as sidewalks are,
هي حق، مثل الأرصفة،
unless we believe that only those
إلى إذا آمنا أن فقط أولئك الذين
with access to a motor vehicle
يركبون سيارات
have a right to safe mobility,
لهم الحق في تنقل آمن،
without the risk of getting killed.
دون خطر التعرض للقتل.
And just as busways are,
ومثل الطرق الخاصة بالحافلات،
protected bikeways also are
فالطرق الخاصة بالدرجات هي أيضاً
a powerful symbol of democracy,
رمز قوي للديمقراطية،
because they show that a citizen on a $30 bicycle
لأنها تظهر أن مواطن في دراجة ب-30 دولار
is equally important
هو بنفس أهمية
to one in a $30,000 car.
مواطن في سيارة ب-30.000 دولار.
And we are living in a unique moment in history.
ونحن نعيش في لحظة تاريخية.
In the next 50 years, more than half of those cities
في ال-50 سنة القادمة، أكثر من نصف هذه المدن
which will exist in the year 2060 will be built.
التي ستكون في 2060، ستبنى.
In many developing country cities,
في كثير من مدن البلدان النامية،
more than 80 and 90 percent
أكثر من 80 و 90 بالمئة
of the city which will exist in 2060
من المدينة التي ستكون في 2060
will be built over the next four or five decades.
ستبنى في العقود الأربعة أو الخمسة القادمة.
But this is not just a matter for developing country cities.
وهذا ليس من شأن البلدان النامية فقط.
In the United States, for example,
في الولايات المتحدة على سبيل المثال،
more than 70 million new homes
أكثر من 70 مليون منزل جديد
must be built over the next 40 or 50 years.
يجب أن يبنى في غضون ال-40 أو ال-50 سنة المقبلة.
That's more than all the homes that today exist
هذا أكثر من عدد المنازل الموجودة اليوم
in Britain, France and Canada put together.
في بريطانيا، فرنسا وكندا معاً.
And I believe that our cities today
و أؤمن أن مدننا اليوم
have severe flaws,
لها عيوب كثيرة،
and that different, better ones could be built.
وأنه يمكن بناء أخرى، مختلفة وأحسن.
What is wrong with our cities today?
مالخطب في مدننا اليوم ؟
Well, for example, if we tell any three-year-old child
في الحقيقة، إذا قلنا لأي طفل في الثالثة من العمر
who is barely learning to speak
الذي يكاد يتعلم الكلام
in any city in the world today,
في أي مدينة من العالم اليوم،
"Watch out, a car,"
&amp;quot;إحذر، سيارة!&amp;quot;
the child will jump in fright,
سيقفز الطفل من الخوف،
and with a very good reason, because there are
مع دافع جيد، لأن هناك
more than 10,000 children who are killed
أكثر من 10.000 طفل يقتلون
by cars every year in the world.
كل عام من طرف السيارات في العالم.
We have had cities for 8,000 years,
لقد كان عندنا مدن ل 8000 الاف سنة،
and children could walk out of home and play.
وكان في وسع الأطفال الخروج من المنزل واللعب.
In fact, only very recently,
في الحقيقة، حديثاً فقط،
towards 1900, there were no cars.
قرابة عام 1900, لم يكون هنالك سيارات.
Cars have been here for really less than 100 years.
السيارات متواجدة هنا منذ أقل من مئة سنة فقط.
They completely changed cities.
لقد غيرت المدن كلياً.
In 1900, for example,
في عام 1900, على سبيل المثال،
nobody was killed by cars in the United States.
لم يقتل أحد من طرف السيارات في الولايات المتحدة.
Only 20 years later,
بعد 20 عام فقط،
between 1920 and 1930,
بين 1920 و 1930،
almost 200,000 people
ما يقارب 200.000 شخص،
were killed by cars in the United States.
قتلوا من طرف السيارات في الولايات المتحدة.
Only in 1925, almost 7,000 children
في عام 1925 فقط، ما يقارب ال-7000 طفل
So we could make different cities,
إذاً في وسعنا إنشاء مدن مختلفة،
cities that will give more priority to human beings
مدن تعطي أكثر أولوية للبشر
than to cars, that will give more public space
من السيارات، التي تعطي فضاء عام أكثر
to human beings than to cars,
للبشر من السيارات،
cities which show great respect
مدن تبدي إحتراماً كبيراً
for those most vulnerable citizens,
لأولئك المواطنين الأكثر عرظة للخطر،
such as children or the elderly.
مثل الأطفال والمسنين.
I will propose to you a couple of ingredients
سأعرض عليكم بعض العناصر
which I think would make cities much better,
التي أعتقد أنها ستجعل مدننا أفضل،
and it would be very simple to implement them
والتي سيسهل دمجها
in the new cities which are only being created.
في المدن الجديدة التي هي في طور الإنشاء.
Hundreds of kilometers of greenways
مئات الكيلومترات من المتنزهات
criss-crossing cities in all directions.
التي تقطع المدينة في كل إتجاه.
Children will walk out of homes into safe spaces.
سيخرج الأطفال من بيوتهم إلى فضاءات آمنة.
They could go for dozens of kilometers safely
يمكنهم قطع عدة كليومترات في أمان
without any risk in wonderful greenways,
دون خطر في متنزهات رائعة،
sort of bicycle highways,
تشبه ممرات الدارجات،
and I would invite you to imagine the following:
و ادعوكم لتخيل مايلي:
a city in which every other street would be
مدينة تكون فيها كل طريق أخرى
a street only for pedestrians and bicycles.
هي طريق للمشاة والدراجات فقط.
In new cities which are going to be built,
في المدن الجديدة التي ستبنى،
this would not be particularly difficult.
لن يكون هذا بالأمر الصعب.
When I was mayor of Bogotá,
عندما كنت عمدة بوغوتا،
in only three years, we were able to create
في غضون 3 سنوات فقط، كنا قادرين على إنشاء
70 kilometers,
70 كيلومتر،
in one of the most dense cities in the world,
في إحدى أكثر مدن العالم كثافةً،
of these bicycle highways.
بممرات الدراجات هذه.
And this changes the way people live,
وهذا يغير طريقة عيش الناس،
move, enjoy the city.
تنقلهم و استمتاعهم بالمدينة.
In this picture, you see in one of the very poor neighborhoods,
في هاته الصورة، ترون في أحد أفقر الأحياء،
we have a luxury pedestrian bicycle street,
لدينا شارع فاخر للمشاة و راكبي الدراجات،
and the cars still in the mud.
والسيارات لازالت عالقة في الوحل.
Of course, I would love to pave this street for cars.
بالطبع، أحب أن أعبد هذه الطريق للسيارات.
But what do we do first?
لكن ما الأولوية؟
Ninety-nine percent of the people in those neighborhoods don't have cars.
تسع و تسعون بالمئة من قاطني هذا الحي لا يملكون سيارات.
But you see, when a city is only being created,
لكن كما ترون، حين تكون المدينة في طور البناء،
it's very easy to incorporate
يكون من السهل جداً دمج،
this kind of infrastructure.
هذا النوع من البنيات التحتية.
Then the city grows around it.
ثم تنمو المدينة من حولها.
And of course this is just a glimpse
وطبعا هذه لمحة فقط
of something which could be much better
عن شيء يمكن أن يكون أحسن بكثير
if we just create it,
إن قمنا فقط بإنشائه،
and it changes the way of life.
وهذا يغير طريقة العيش.
And the second ingredient, which would solve mobility,
والعنصر الثاني الذي سيحل مشكلة التنقل،
that very difficult challenge in developing countries,
هذا التحدي الكبير في المدن النامية،
in a very low-cost and simple way,
بتكاليف ضئيلة و طريقة بسيطة،
would be to have hundreds of kilometers
هو الحصول على مئات الكيلومترات
of streets only for buses,
من الطرق مخصصة للحافلات فقط،
buses and bicycles and pedestrians.
للحافلات، المشاة و راكبي الدراجات.
This would be, again, a very low-cost solution
سيكون هذا حلاً، ذو تكاليف ضئيلة ايظاً
if implemented from the start,
إذا تم دمجه منذ البداية،
low cost, pleasant transit
تكاليف ضئيلة، عبور سهل
with natural sunlight.
تحت ضوء الشمس الطبيعي.
But unfortunately, reality is not as good
لكن لسوء الحظ ، الحقيقة ليست جيدة
as my dreams.
بقدر أحلامي.
Because of private property of land
لأنه بسبب الملكية الخاصة للأراضي،
and high land prices,
وسعرها الباهظ،
all developing country cities have a large problem of slums.
كل مدن البلدان النامية لديها مشكل الأحياء العشوائية.
In my country of Colombia, almost half the homes
في بلدي كولومبيا، تقريباً نصف الديار،
in cities initially were illegal developments.
تطورت بطريقة غير شرعية في البداية.
And of course it's very difficult to have
و بالطبع صعب الحصول على
mass transit or to use bicycles in such environments.
نقل واسع أو إستعمال دارجات في محيط مماثل.
But even legal developments
وحتى التوسعات القانونية،
have also been located in the wrong places,
تقع في المناطق الغير مناسبة،
very far from the city centers
بعيدة جداً عن مركز المدينة
where it's impossible to provide
أين يكون من المستحيل توفير
low-cost, high-frequency public transport.
نقل عام مستمر، بسعر منخفض.
As a Latin American, and Latin America
بصفتي من أمريكا الجنوبية، وجنوب أمريكا
was the most recently organized region in the world,
كانت أخر منطقة نظمت في العالم،
I would recommend, respectfully, passionately,
انصح بإحترام، بشغف،
to those countries which are yet to urbanize --
تلك البلدان التي لم تتحول معظمها إلى مدن--
Latin America went from 40 percent urban in 1950
أمريكا اللاتينية انتقلت من 40% حضرية في 1950
to 80 percent urban in 2010 --
إلى 80% حضرية في 2010--
I would recommend Asian and African countries
انصح البلدان الأسيوية والإفريقية
which are yet to urbanize,
المقبلة على التمدن،
such as India which is only 33 percent urban now,
مثل الهند المتمدنة بنسبة 33% فقط الأن،
that governments should acquire all land around cities.
بأن تكسب الحكومة كل الأراضي حول المدن.
In this way, their cities could grow in the right places
فهكذا، ستنمو مدنهم في الأماكن المناسبة
with the right spaces, with the parks,
بالفضاءات المناسبة، بالحدائق،
with the greenways, with the busways.
بالمتنزهات، بالطرق الخاصة للحافلات.
The cities we are going to build
المدن التي سنبنيها
over the next 50 years
خلال ال-50 سنة المقبلة
will determine quality of life and even happiness
ستحدد جودة العيش وحتى السعادة
for billions of people towards the future.
لمليارات من الناس عبر المستقبل.
What a fantastic opportunity for leaders
يالها من فرصة للزعماء
and many young leaders to come,
والقادة الشبان للمجيء،
especially in the developing countries.
خاصة في البلدان النامية.
They can create a much happier life
بإمكانهم تأسيس حياة أسعد بكثير
for billions towards the future.
لمليارات من الناس عبر المستقبل.
I am sure, I am optimistic,
أنا واثق، أنا متفائل،
that they will make cities better
أنهم سيجعلون المدن أفضل
than our most ambitious dreams.
من أكثر أحلامنا طموحاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)